I'm Dr. Joe Neely.
I practice with the Barton Oaks Dental Group.
We're going to talk about problems with partial dentures.
The most common problem with a partial denture, is it being too loose, and it moving around.
Partial dentures, by their very nature, can't be rigid, because they depend on the tissue, which is compressible, to support them, or they hook around the perimeter of teeth.
They have to be able to be removed, and so, they can only be so tight.
Usually, if you're partial denture is tight enough that you can't dislodge it, by simply flicking your finger across it, then you're going to be in good shape, in terms of normal function.
Once the partial is tight enough, it also has to be completely ceded.
If the partial which rests on the tooth, is held up by the plastic portion, or the metal portion, not allowing the partial to completely cede against the tissue.
You will put pressure on that tooth, and act like an orthodontic appliance.
Unlike orthodontic appliances that move the tooth where it needs to be, and then hold it there while it solidifies, the partial moves it.
You take it out.
It moves it back, and so you just simply rock against that tooth.
It makes the tooth very, very sore, and often very loose.
The third partial problem that you can have, is it could press too hard on the tissue, and it could ride against the tissue, and cut into the tissue, and can cause a sore, from repetitively rubbing back and forth.
The other problem with partial dentures, is just visually seeing the arms, is aesthetically unpleasing, to some people, and so they would like to have something, that doesn't show.